Okay, in this video then, we're going to
talk about the skill sets, or at least
some of the skill sets required for a
project manager.
And actually, also, we're
going to include some of
the skill sets required
for team members as well.
Now, the number one job skill,
as we've mentioned several times,
number one job skill for a project manager
is communication.
That is why you hire a project manager to
communicate.
A project manager is a good communicator.
A project manager is
someone that can get tasks
moving along and team
members working together.
That is what makes a project manager.
Not necessarily they have technical
skills.
Project manager, and far as PMI is
concerned, a project manager does not
necessarily need to have deep technical
skills.
They need to know a thing or two about
what they're managing, obviously,
but they don't have to be a technical
expert.
They have to be able to manage.
technical experts.
They're going to be hiring technical
experts and making sure then things are
moving along and basically managing these
technical experts.
So communication then is the number one
job skill for a project manager.
And there's an entire knowledge area on
communication.
Entire set of videos, entire lesson on
communication managers.
Right.
Now also along with this then,
right?
There's going to be conflicts where we're
going to have conflicts, disagreements,
So a project manager is
someone that can manage
these conflicts, not
necessarily resolve conflicts.
There's a difference doing conflict
resolution and conflict management.
You can't always resolve a conflict,
but certainly you can manage a conflict so
it doesn't have a negative impact on the
project.
And that's really what conflict management
refers to.
So that's a key skill to have for a
project manager.
And there's a separate video altogether on
conflict management.
Also, cultural awareness, political
differences, cultural differences,
personal differences,
this is going to play
a huge part, right, as managing your team.
You've got team members in different
countries.
So, you know, being aware of cultural
differences, being aware of personal
differences and political differences as
well.
Now, when we're talking
about political differences,
we're talking about
office politics here, right?
So, again, a project manager is someone
that can communicate at all levels.
They can communicate with all different
stakeholders and take all of these into
consideration and adjust a communication
style accordingly.
So cultural differences also then includes
things like diversity, diversity and
inclusion, making sure that nobody is left
out.
And again, this goes to all the different
types of differences, cultural,
political, personal differences,
and so on and so forth.
So a project manager is someone,
you know, you have to have these skill
sets to be able to navigate through all of
these, you know, all of all the
stakeholders, you know, all the different
types of stakeholders.
And obviously decision making,
right.
So that's a major skill set for a project
manager.
You have to make decisions.
A project, remember a project for a
project manager, for a command and control
project manager, they are accountable for
the project.
So they need to be able to make decisions
on that project.
They are one of the major decision makers,
you know, on the actual project.
Tactical decision making, not necessarily
strategic decision making.
Strategic decision making rests with the
project leadership team.
But day-to-day, tactical decision-making,
that's going to come
with the project manager.
And because there are so many stakeholders
involved, there's going to be meetings and
focus groups and workshops and
brainstorming sessions.
Who's facilitating all of those?
The project manager.
Project manager is going to be
facilitating all of these different
meetings and focus groups and so and so
forth.
So you need to have facilitation skills,
meeting management, and so and so forth.
Of course, leadership is a major skill.
Part of leadership is also collaboration.
You are managing people.
So managing people involves leadership.
And this whole section is about the people
domain, which really is leadership.
And part of being a leader is also
negotiating, negotiating contracts,
negotiating work, negotiating
service level agreements,
again, all major skill
sets for a project manager.
And this also overlaps with procurement.
We'll be covering negotiation again in
procurement management as well.
Because, again, you might be negotiating
contracts.
but certainly negotiating the
work for team members and
service level agreements
and so and so and so forth.
In the Agile world, it's the court-unquote
project manager, right?
Not really a project manager.
They are known as a team facilitator and
they are not the command and control.
They are the servant leader.
So servant leadership is very important
and actually servant leadership,
although it is required in Agile,
I mean technically servant leadership is
also a part of a project manager skill set
anyway.
Basically supporting
the team, making sure the
team has the tools to
actually perform the work.
At the same time, you're removing any
barriers, any impediments, any blockers,
right, to progress.
So project manager has to have those
skills as well.
Something that we mentioned on a prior
video, team building.
Your project is only as good as your team.
So you want your team members to get to
know one another.
You want your team members to work
cohesively together.
That's all part of team building.
So that's a skill set for a project
manager as well.
And there's going to be different skill
sets required or different procedures
required for team building
based on whether team members
are face to face or whether
they're working remotely.
And of course, also being able to appraise
your team members.
So that's a major skill set, team skill
appraisal, evaluating team members.
So on a separate video, we're going to be
covering the strengths and weaknesses.
We're going to be covering SWAT analysis
as it pertains to your team.
But as a project manager, you need to be
able to identify, or rather you need to be
able to help the team identify their
strengths and weaknesses.
So we're going to cover that in a bit more
detail on a separate video.
But the whole idea also
behind this is to build trust
amongst team members so
that they can collaborate, right?
So, you know, part of team building is
building trust amongst team members.
As a general rule, when
team members get to know one
another, they easily work
a lot better together, right?
And then also strengths and weaknesses,
weaknesses refers to improvement.
opportunities, right?
Training, for example.
And training doesn't have to be,
you know, they take in a day off or two
days off and sitting in a class,
but training could be on the job training,
job shadowing, or even
just reading a manual, you
know, and following the
manual and so and and so forth.
But again, they need to improve,
right, need to improve their skill sets.
And then also team member preferences and
aspirations, right?
That's something that often gets
overlooked in in many organizations,
especially at a project level.
Remember, the number one success factor on
a project is stakeholder engagement.
Again, your team members are stakeholders
on your project.
And so you want to get the best out of
your team.
You want to engage your team.
So you want to place your team members on
the right role.
So you want to identify what their
preference is in aspirational.
are.
If they're not happy in a particular role,
then they're not going
to excel in that role.
They're not going to be engaged in that
role.
So part of being a project manager,
you know, one of your skill sets is to be
able to, again, work
with your team members,
right, collaborate with your team, right?
Put them in the position,
put them in, you know,
give them the tasks
that they are engaged in.
Now, talking of which then, let's briefly
talk about some skill
sets for team members.
So these are a couple of terms, two terms
that you will come across on the exam.
Definitely you need to know T-shaped
skills and I-shaped skills.
Right.
So, and this really is kind of like the
T-shaped is really preferred for agile
team, but let's talk about what the
difference is.
Let's talk about I-shaped first.
I-shaped skills basically means that you
have depths of knowledge in one area.
You are a subject matter expert in this
one area.
And that's really what you're focused on.
Any other skill sets or anything
else you really don't know
much about, but you're a subject
matter expert in this one area.
Whereas with T-shaped skills,
you have brets of knowledge,
or rather you have depth
of knowledge in one area.
So you are a technical
expert in one area, but you also
have some breadth of
knowledge in other areas as well.
And some of these other areas then could
include, for example, management skills,
leadership skills as well as you have
these technical skills as well.
And it's T-shaped skills that is preferred
in an agile team.
In an agile team, remember, there you are
what's known as a self-organizing team.
So you're a self-organizing team.
The team themselves are responsible for
the leadership, right, in an agile and an
agile project, the team themselves
are responsible for the leadership, right?
In a predictive project, it's a project
manager that's responsible, but in an
agile project, the entire team is
responsible.
And so they have, they are what's known as
a self-organizing team.
And in order to be a
self-organizing team, right,
then you need to have
these T-shaped skills, right?
So you have skills in one area,
right, deep skills in one area,
but then you can diversify.
And so you can work in other areas as
well.
And that's why, or rather, that's how
agile teams work together.
So that's the basic difference in between
T-shaped skills and I-shaped skills.
So a couple of skill sets required for
team members.